I'm with Ray Corti uh friend of many
years over 50 and uh the founding pastor
of the Seven Rivers Presbyterian Church
uh it'd be impossible for us to
Chronicle our friendship over the 50
years uh that we've known one another
but Ry maybe you could spend to the
important of lasting friendships and
Ministry well I think obviously they're
really important because Ministry is
hard you know it's got a lot of gut
punches to it it's exhausting um and
it's Relentless you know we like said to
the year as soon as you say Amen on
Sunday morning the clock's ticking um uh
for the next weekend and and it doesn't
really the calendar doesn't care whether
you're sick your wife's sick um what
other crises you face your kids are
struggling um the schedule's unrelenting
so um you know you don't want to quit um
but you're exhausted and sometimes you
just don't know if you got it you know
you just don't know if you can keep on
and
um um I had an experience with my uh
Sons I took my two sons and two
son-in-laws um walking the Inca hiking
the Inca Trail to Machu Picchu and the
hardest part of the hike about five
straight hours uphill with my sons and
they got way ahead of me they abandoned
me
um but you know when I I finally got to
the top of the summit uh and I just
didn't even know if I could make it it
was steep right at the end and my
youngest son saw me at the top and he
called down to me started cheering me on
and then he ran down and took my
backpack put his arm under me and took
me to the top I'll never forget it and
and that's what uh friendship's like in
Ministry is um you don't want to quit
but sometimes you just can't find uh it
in you to keep going and and um honestly
Mike we're talking because you've been
that friend to me again and again over
the course of ministry I'm deeply
grateful for that I know you you've been
that for so
many well uh obviously uh you hold uh a
very dear place in my heart Ray thank
you and I feel the same but you started
on your family you haven't done this
alone you and Diane have been together a
long time you have children and
grandchildren uh tell us a little bit
about your
family yeah you know gosh we we are uh
blessed we've got we got four
children um our uh our oldest son um
lives in Tallahassee he's in political
fundraising he and his wife involved in
a church and in Christian School just
picture of God's faithfulness you know
we started a Christian School here and
our older son hated it he hated being in
it he um was mad um and I didn't blame
blame him you know um he was the top
grade there was no older guys in it to
kind of follow after that means all his
sports teams were terrible you know they
were ninth graders playing seniors at
other schools and um now he's been on
the school board of a a classical
Christian School in Tallahassee helping
to form that all his kids go there and
that's that's right down my daughter in
Texas uh is actually working just
yesterday we're talking about bylaws at
the Christian school she's helping to
create and um um our daughter in Orlando
she and her husband are in meshed in
inner city um Ministry and guess what
they started a school um this year in
inner city Orlando and our younger son
um Tucker works with his brother in
Tallahassee so 10 grandkids uh and and
yeah the Delight of our
life I'm sure and how long have you and
Diane been married Diane and I have been
uh married will be 45 years this uh
summer my wife's um didn't grow up in
the faith she was converted in college
at Arizona State
University uh she had no idea what
church was like or um she said she can't
consciously remember meeting a Christian
um in her childhood ever until she went
to
college um so she uh she just brings
this feisty Zeal for people
relationship and um has uh has been a
great uh partner and companion and um
people in our church adore
her wonderful uh you were going from a
senior pastor at Crystal River to
founding Pastor uh at Seven Rivers to
founding pastor and uh you all have
transitioned to the next uh Pastor who
was on your staff your roles changing
just a little bit about that that
and a short encapsulation of the story
of Seven Rivers if you can yeah I heard
a guy speak a number of years ago at a
conference um and it kind of really uh I
was amazed he was great great uh
preacher speaker and he was an assistant
pastor at his church and I thought
where's the senior pastor I mean this
was a conference hundreds of thousands
of people around the world
were tuned into this and I actually
spoke to him afterwards and and he gave
me the number of the senior pastor and
and guy gave me some great advice on how
you um cultivate you know he said the
Young Eagles and let them fly you know
and so we really started a number of
years ago just um formed a pastoral team
and I've just considered myself a part
of that team for years and so I'm not
going to be the I am not the senior
pastor any longer but I am uh still a
part of the Pastoral team and it doesn't
doesn't feel like that much of a change
we've just had a pastoral team that's
been laboring here together for a number
of years so excited that God provided
one of those Young Eagles to be ready
and and already see energy that they're
bringing and and um blessing to this
ministry so yeah this church is unusual
uhh for the PCA I suppose because it's
really a small town north of
Tampa uh so when we came here you know
this town didn't have a Target it didn't
have a Starbucks it didn't have a
Chick-fil-A it didn't have well guess
what that's 41 years ago and there's no
target there's no Starbucks and there's
no Chick-fil-A um yet so um you know you
kind of had a reluctant Pastor my wife's
from Chicago I'm from Miami we we were
really small town people I mean we went
to school in RTS in Jackson Mississippi
and and I hated that all these guys
would go to little towns in Mississippi
and it's like why don't they go where
their people you know the the gospel um
we want to reach people and um and here
I ended up in this little tiny um
town and um but I I just say um Through
The Years God you know this is a place
where retirees come and and I know we
were told When We Were Young that if you
don't reach people when they're in in um
you know in their teens and in their
early 20s and that's when everybody's
converted and that's why student
Ministry is so important important and
I've seen no difference um retirees that
move here leave behind their job their
family their culture their their sense
of purpose and meaning and everything
else they come here they're just sitting
ducks for the
gospel and uh anyway we've had a blast
and watch God do something really sweet
he's blessed that Ministry tremendously
can't wait to celebrate with you all
this weekend thank you this question
comes from David Cassidy our mutual
friend uh you've served joyfully
faithfully and humbly looking back what
are two or three things that you know
now that you really know now that you
thought you knew when you
started well I I'm GNA narrow it down to
one thing because it really did change
my life and and uh in Ministry from when
I
started um you know I was uh I was a
hard driving um Earnest hard worker but
my goal was
um to validate myself before God and I
didn't understand I I I you know I grew
up in the church I I love Jesus I love
the Bible I I love church um but I
didn't understand um the imputation of
Christ's righteousness I knew Jesus was
my sin Bearer I knew I was going to
heaven um I wanted other people to go to
heaven too um but I didn't uh I didn't
know what it was like to have the
Delight of God um I didn't know what it
was like to have the kiss of the
prodigal son I didn't see myself as a
prodigal son I was a proud older brother
and I didn't even get that Parable I
didn't even know the older brother was
in that story really it's not that's not
what it's called you know they didn't
call it the parable the older brother
and yet it's really about the older
brother um he's the one who doesn't even
end up in the party um and uh through uh
through a number of mentors like but but
you know like Martin Luther and Jack
Miller
um came to understand the gospel and and
largely came to understand it because
people in our church were telling me how
exhausted they were and um how um you
know if if any man is in Christ you know
he's a new creature old passed away new
come the new comes and they're not
experiencing the new they didn't have
any power they didn't have any joy and I
was just um hands the plown no turning
back you know um driving our
congregation ation it was a pretty sober
realization to realize that my my being
a minister my being in church planting
my starting a church in a school all of
that was a grand project of self
validation trying to earn favor with God
not realizing that Jesus had already
done that for me and that realization
changed everything made me a made me a
better friend made me a sweeter husband
made me um uh more relational made me
see my own sins made me
a more repentant uh person um made me um
you know I started to love the
congregation instead of just see them as
a project to uh to establish my own
worth good good stuff Ray thank you uh
you've got a young Seminary grad and his
wife before you and they're entering
into Ministry uh what would you say to
them regarding the possibilities of
pitfall calls the priorities that
they'll encounter in the calling run run
for your
life no honestly I'd say the opposite
I'd say uh I think Ministry holds the
possibility for the best possible life
that you could
imagine um I have I I have loved it I
love it um and uh I mean gosh who gets a
front row seat to watch um Jesus seek
and save the lost you know um so what
I'd say to young people is so you know
that that fear that all the pressure
Ministry and the criticism and a culture
that's that's hostile to the church and
is going to damage their family and
damage their um children I just say
don't make an adversary out of uh don't
don't don't Pit family and Ministry
against um each other you I hear these
people say my family comes first I think
that's garbage Jesus comes first um and
uh and I don't think your family's ah
head of the church why should they they
be they're both beautiful they're both
important um lead your family to love
the church lead your family into
Ministry lead your family to die for the
mission to love the bride of Christ and
uh and I think the greater danger in our
world is the the narcissism of our
culture the self-absorption the um uh
you know the massive salaries our
children are making and and all the you
know um and I I think that this calling
allows us to actually lead our family to
collectively Embrace a mission of dying
for Jesus it's the best life there
is good good word I me the one who gives
up life is the one who finds it right so
amen uh last question uh you really
preached one of the most stirring
sermons at General Assembly I know you
probably don't remember most of it but
it was called a a beautiful
Orthodoxy and um and I I'm just asking
how would you assess the the landscape
of our
denomination and what would you say to
us going forward to to act in a unified
way uh for the sake of a mission that's
greater than
us well um there are certainly moments
of discouragement uh regarding the
health of our denomination I think uh in
some ways the PCA is floundering I think
it's drifted from its original um
mission
um I think today for many in the PCA it
it seems that their mission what really
animates them is doctrinal and
confessional
Precision um we see more you know even
taking issue like women women's
involvement in the church and everything
we seem more interested in excluding
women from Ministry than employing them
and every way possible and and
benefiting from their gifts and so you
know I don't think we have to make a
choice between doctrinal Fidelity and
missional passion um I I don't think you
can have one without the other and
you're not really doctrinally faithful
in other words we're worried about
things like the role of women in our
churches when you can look across the
span of our denomination and find the
majority of churches uh reach virtually
no one they have almost no one joining
through profession of Faith um in their
um statistics so um you know Jesus uh
you made mention of the the older
brother the The Prodigal Son Parable
earlier you know at the point of the
parable what is it Jesus is chiding
older brothers because they're
critiquing him because he eats with
prostitutes and tax collectors eats with
the the uh the outcast of culture and he
chides them because the older brother
doesn't search for the younger brother
um and basically he says to them why do
I eat with tax collectors and
prostitutes he says to the Pharisees
because you don't that's why I came into
this world so I think um the PCA my
longing is that they would more robustly
embrace the mission of Jesus to seek and
save the lost and um and of course no
abandonment of doctrinal fidelity ever
that would be utterly
foolish Ray uh great words uh passionate
uh you will be serving the PCA and
really the the kingdom for for many
years and um thank you for this time I
like loved it and and by the way I love
the PCA I'm not going anywhere I'm all
in for I know you're
not blessings thank you all right buddy